In Vietnam,
They say that a smile makes you look 10 years younger.
In this country marked by so much...
So many tragedies,
so many wars,
and today, due to increasingly frequent natural disasters,
if everyone looks ten years younger,
that's because here,
Whatever happens,
Happiness is essential.
To struggle against,
fight,
not to complain,
react,
survive,
to force destiny,
to overcome the elements
These are the watchwords of an entire population that displays unfailing energy in the face of the wrath of the monsoon, which from spring onwards plunges the center of the country into expected but increasingly virulent turmoil year after year.
Originally from Guangbin province,
A woman decided to fight against the fury of the elements and their dramatic consequences.
Her name is
Link.
Ever since I was very little,
I have always loved nature.
That's why I decided to study agronomy.
And now,
I am lucky with my job to truly do what I love.
I work for a government organization committed to environmental protection and which aims to safeguard natural resources as best as possible.
The organization has a presence all over the world, and particularly here.
in Vietnam.
My goal in my work is not only to protect the environment,
but above all, to seek to help people in difficulty,
by trying to improve their living conditions.
In Vietnam,
Water is everywhere.
source of life.
One should not be fooled by its apparent tranquility.
With global warming,
The monsoon becomes less predictable and its effects are amplified by an unleashing of the elements.
The village loudspeakers,
Radio and especially television allow residents to be informed.
The Dong Hoi broadcasting center regularly experiences the effects of the monsoon.
Flood,
destruction of the forest,
erosion,
The sand is invading the shores,
The earth changes its contours.
The water is rising, yet drought looms.
But the energy of the Vietnamese is there to counter the effects of nature.
These news images are a valuable source of information for Lien.
Because after the disasters,
Her job is to realize this for herself.
on the ground,
actions to be taken.
I must admit that...
What is difficult in my daily work,
It's about feeling alone and helpless in the face of difficulties.
Fortunately,
with my colleagues,
We share the same beliefs.
Together,
We seek to spread the idea that we must do everything possible to protect natural resources and that we must find solutions to improve people's living conditions.
Oh,
Good morning !
How did it go?
The last flood?
It's already been two months.
The water rose all the way to the roof.
At the level of the roof of the house?
Yes,
up to the roof.
And what did you do when the water arrived?
Fortunately,
There was a rescue team that evacuated us.
We're here today to see what we can do for you.
Has anyone come by to help you since then?
Yes,
the local manager.
From the village, this woman has lost everything; her house has already collapsed several times in recent years, swept away by tornadoes. Each time, she rebuilt it until the day she made a big decision last year with
With all her savings, she bought several tons of cement to build a solid house before the rainy season, but she was ignoring climate change, because against all odds
Rains from Ille-le-Vienne suddenly fell on the village with the announcement of spring and all the cement was lost.
All my brothers and sisters rushed over.
There are those who brought me rice,
others, drinking water,
because we no longer had any possibility of obtaining drinking water.
The Ienne and the women of the Women Union association are seeking to find a solution so that she finally has a solid roof over her head.
Kuang Bin province,
in the center of the country,
has been hit by more than thirty typhoons in the last 50 years.
And we are seeing that floods are now much more violent than those that occurred during the first half of the last century.
There you see,
These are images from last year's flood.
in October 2007.
We,
journalists,
We went there immediately to do an on-site report.
The water rose up to the roof and there were things floating everywhere.
Everything was destroyed.
Right after that,
The military arrived to intervene.
There,
You see,
to access the flooded areas,
We take the rescue boats.
Because they are the only ones capable of going against the current.
The small boats belonging to the locals are not powerful enough.
They risk being swept away by the force of the current.
Today,
The effects of the monsoon have become impossible to predict.
And the peaks of the phenomenon are becoming increasingly difficult to imagine.
Causing floods and landslides that have affected many victims.
While the effects of the monsoon are unpredictable,
the scenario,
him,
is always the same.
It all starts at the weather center.
The figures for the instruments speak for themselves.
Depression,
wind acceleration,
cloudy disturbances,
formation of pockets of warm air in opposition to masses of cold air.
Six months a year,
Vietnam is under close surveillance.
It's fortunate that the government is concerned about at-risk regions that are isolated.
That's why we've set up a radio communication system for remote areas that don't get television reception.
Just before the floods,
Residents are warned by radio depending on the level of danger.
For example,
if a disaster is looming,
They issue alerts every hour, and even every half hour if necessary.
To mobilize against the floods,
Consider regrouping urgently and organizing the protection of people and property.
This is an exercise.
This is an alert exercise.
In case of an alert,
even with resources that may seem paltry,
Everyone is mobilizing to fight against a possible rise in water levels.
When there is a flood,
Does the manager summon you directly to the location each time?
Yes,
That's it.
Do people come in groups?
Yes,
in groups or individually.
All the residents come to lend a hand.
When a storm or cyclone is approaching,
We only have a few hours to prepare and find the right ways to protect ourselves against the floods.
Normally,
the water remains at that level,
but...
As soon as it starts to rain,
It's rising very, very quickly.
How high does it go?
The water can rise above the roofs of the houses.
those that can be seen over there.
And the water flows down to these rice paddies,
So, what about those opposite us?
Yes,
all the way to the rice paddies,
all the way to the field that could be seen at the foot of the mountains.
A small, newly dug canal,
A simple dam of leaves will contain the current and divert the water below the rice paddies.
Lien knows all the methods the villagers use to protect themselves.
Each time, she is equally impressed by the energy he puts into facing the elements.
In general,
after the flood,
There are landslides.
The trees are being uprooted, and so people are finding themselves in a truly catastrophic situation.
And by the time the water recedes,
It takes at least 5 to 7 days.
Several rescuers told me that sometimes,
They arrive too late to intervene.
When people disappear,
The rescuers are taking it very badly.
There are people who try to help others,
but who consequently put themselves in danger to the point that some disappear in turn.
Just after this flood,
Not only did people in the region mobilize,
but also all the people of the country.
They sent food,
They supported them.
You see.
Aid has arrived from absolutely everywhere.
A testament to this solidarity so prevalent in Vietnam,
The IEN is working to raise awareness among remote populations about the risk of flooding.
In particular, children from the poorest families,
those who live on small boats and are the first to be exposed to the danger of the monsoon.
Lien's message is clear.
It is absolutely essential that children get into the habit of wearing life jackets to protect themselves from drowning, even when going to school as soon as the weather presents risks.
When she participates in the distribution of life jackets,
She can't help but think that,
amidst the general good cheer,
A deep distress is hidden beneath the surface.
that of the memory of the parents of some of her children,
disappeared during the last flood.
Môn giã căng căng đời tựa Ta mê lây chung vui
Còng phân chia lòng nói tiếng cười
Cùng nắm tay ta kia kinh sanh nơi
Nào cho nhau những gì
In the Guangbin region,
Many animals have died.
I went there and realized what it represented.
this loss of livestock is a problem for families who are very poor.
During the disaster,
People no longer care about what they own.
But afterwards,
They realize the economic loss this represents for them.
That's huge.
I was really very touched and I feel very unhappy for them.
Even when you've lost everything,
We keep smiling.
We couldn't do anything.
I've lost everything.
The house,
the furniture.
The harvests,
Absolutely everything.
We can no longer adapt to the climate.
like in the old days.
That's how it is now.
That's how it is.
When you've lost everything,
We keep smiling.
even when the dikes,
built to retain rainwater and water from streams,
do not resist,
with dramatic consequences for people,
housing,
crops and infrastructure.
It went up to this point.
This is truly the biggest flood I've ever seen.
But you know,
This year,
I'm really afraid it will be even worse than last year's.
Even though last year's was already incredible.
It covered everything.
the road,
the trees,
Everything was underwater.
There were tree trunks everywhere,
It even rose right up to the electric fence.
practically at rooftop level.
The state will have to consider rebuilding the bridge because now,
when the cars come barreling down the road,
Accidents happen.
Because there are people who live in very remote forested areas,
in my work,
Access conditions are sometimes very difficult.
For example,
There are roads inaccessible by car.
Sometimes,
They are even inaccessible by car.
It's a target on a moped.
It can take 5 to 6 hours of walking to get there.
In addition,
You have to climb the mountain.
It's sometimes very hard for someone like me to go there.
The living conditions are really not comfortable for sleeping.
The same applies to food,
not to mention the hygiene conditions.
What is all this wood you're transporting?
It was wood that was causing an obstruction at the foot of the dam.
because of the floods.
Are you using it to make a fire?
Yes,
That's it.
Only for making a fire.
And if we don't pick it up,
What's going on?
If we don't pick it up,
This prevents water from flowing into the dam.
Things are moving.
And you're going in pairs to collect all that wood?
Yes,
We do this every day.
Every day ?
Yes,
only during this period when there are heavy rains.
As in previous years,
We do this every year.
Was it the same last year?
Yes,
Yes.
Oh yes,
It's always like that.
Another dam has been destroyed by the storm.
Lien is pleased to see that attitudes are changing,
since the farmers chose to recover the dead wood that was blocking the dam,
rather than going to cut down trees in the forest.
Traditionally,
if the peasants cut down the wood,
It's simply to make a fire.
for the...
kitchen.
With the local officials she meets regularly in the field,
Lien seeks to assess the human impact that can amplify the effects of the monsoon.
The more we deforest,
The faster the water flows, the more weakened the remaining trees become.
The uncontrolled exploitation of forests destroys the balance of nature and the work of the Ienne consists of informing the villagers of the risks they are posing to the environment.
Risks whose consequences are visible as soon as one ventures into the mountains.
Before,
There were trees.
NOW,
All the greats have disappeared.
With landslides,
the water can no longer drain properly.
But then,
The rice paddies have disappeared.
those below are no longer supplied with water.
Look at,
Before, it was all covered in trees, and now there aren't many left.
Every time it rains,
Any area where there are no more trees is at risk of causing landslides.
The earth collapses below and completely shifts the dam.
There is also a lot of dead wood and branches that block the proper drainage of water.
So that's good.
if the inhabitants get rid of this wood and remove all the soil so that the water can flow normally.
I was born and raised in a very mountainous region,
where there were many trees.
When I was a child,
I spent my time riding and playing in the forest near my home.
And that's also why I love my job so much.
If Lienne is so sensitive to the problems caused by the monsoon,
This is because his parents are also regularly confronted with climatic phenomena.
When she visits her family,
People always talk about the last flood.
The biggest flood in the last ten years,
I'm sure of it.
It's really the same one as last year.
That day,
There wasn't any more of it all day.
And it's late,
late afternoon,
around 7pm,
that's when it really began.
We finished dinner and just as we were getting ready to go to bed,
there,
Everything happened so fast.
Suddenly,
The water began to rise,
to climb at an incredible speed.
Water,
It reached above the knee.
We.
And then,
We had only one idea left,
It's about seeking refuge elsewhere.
We said to ourselves,
Too bad about the furniture,
We couldn't save them.
There were plenty of them,
full of objects floating all around us.
Let's show each other how high it's gone.
He had so much, or more, all day long.
The water rose so fast.
Listen,
around 2 a.m.,
She had made it this far.
Look at,
That's crazy!
Did you see the mark?
You can see the difference in color.
So what?
Where did you put your things?
Where were they?
Come,
Follow me,
I'll show you.
I put them in the attic.
Family affairs,
like cushions,
the covers,
all of that,
there.
We put them up there.
In his native village,
Everyone knows about Lien's commitment.
And the neighbors do not hesitate to ask her for help when it comes to planting.
Oh Lien,
what are you doing ?
Are you planting something?
Yes,
These are wind trees.
Herbs against the wind?
Yes,
It's holding up well.
Do you have any at home?
No,
Not yet,
But could you pass us a few?
No problem,
You just have to help yourself.
Take several.
We're going to plant them.
You see these plants,
They are one year old.
Now is the perfect time to plant them.
A handful of soil and that's it.
In your opinion,
Tell me,
How do you feel about the climate change?
What we can say,
that's because last year,
There was a very severe flood.
And this climate change,
Do you think it's going to continue to deteriorate?
Yes,
I'm afraid of it.
Already,
We realize that the temperature is starting to rise.
It's getting hotter and hotter.
The climate is not reassuring and on top of that, so many trees have been cut down.
Replanting is absolutely necessary to compensate for the negative effects of the climate.
We really need to replant.
Is planting trees only to combat flooding, or do you think there are other positive effects?
I don't know, but when I plant a tree in the ground,
That reassures me.
Deforestation coupled with rising sea levels is causing a climate imbalance that is having a severe impact here.
in the Kuan Bin region.
On the coast,
invaded by sand dunes,
Desertification looms.
Fortunately,
young entrepreneurs like Mr.
Vodainya are taking matters into their own hands.
The climate has changed a lot here.
When I arrived,
It was very, very hot.
The ground,
the forests,
the few trees that grew all around,
Everything was there, but completely dried out.
The sand was everywhere.
It was like a desert here.
Traditionally,
plants that grow along the coastline,
like mangroves,
that one would normally find in these regions but which are disappearing,
play a fundamental role in the protection of coastlines.
They prevent erosion.
They stabilize the dunes.
slow down the floods.
slow down the effects of cyclones.
tide rats,
and thus reduce climate warming.
Mr. Vaudaïgnat is of the same generation as Lienne.
And it is with the same conviction that he decided to change the appearance of the coastline by planting hundreds of thousands of trees on his property every year.
For him,
This is the best way to protect the Vietnam of tomorrow.
He wants to open up Vietnam, particularly to ecotourism.
The fuel shortage in the coastal region is so severe that most of the crops have been cut down.
giving way to sand dunes.
Apart from a few private initiatives like that of Mr.
Vodania,
Various international organizations have endeavored in recent decades to combat the formation of sand dunes by planting trees.
But the attempts have often been unsuccessful.
the young plants having been destroyed to make firewood.
When I was young,
I never would have imagined what my life would be like later.
When I arrived at high school,
I became aware of this through the news on television.
with the newspapers,
of all the problems.
related to deforestation.
Today I realize that there will always be work for me in this sector.
Given everything that needs to be done.
This work involves making villagers understand that trees play a vital role as a barrier against water.
the winds and the sand.
You know,
What you need to understand here is
It's because the people are very poor.
If we don't take care of the fences,
It's certain they will come to steal wood to make a fire.
It is essential to put up barriers if we want to plant trees.
Anyway,
This is the only way to stop the dune.
And then there's the sand piling up at the foot of the fences,
It ends up creating an effective barrier against the wind.
Look at,
the beach was noticeably lower before.
You see there,
before this tree,
It rose to 2.50 meters.
And now,
It's no higher than that.
Encouraging farmers like Mr.
Vaudaïna reinforces Lienne's conviction.
For her,
There is no such thing as fate, and there is still hope.
A better world.
I come from a poor family,
but I was much luckier than others in being able to go to school.
And now,
It is my turn to give back what I have been given by helping people in difficulty and protecting their environment.
This quest for a better world,
That's also what Mr.
Nguyen Thanh Hen and his family.
By repeatedly losing all his crops,
This former farmer decided to change his life and become a fisherman.
A prime example of the Vietnamese people's ability to adapt.
We can't go fishing far because unfortunately we only have a small boat.
Since my brothers, a few friends, and I didn't have enough money,
we put all our...
our shared savings.
And that's how I was able to buy a share of this boat.
So there are five of us families sharing it in order to be able to work.
But in this region,
traditionally,
There are two seasons in the year.
For six months,
The sea is rather calm.
And for another six months,
You could say she's rather agitated.
But in recent years,
Everything has changed.
The tidal cycle is different,
Water levels are changing.
And now,
the normal cycle,
that is to say, the fact that the sea should change every six months,
is no longer respected at all.
Faced with the delta, which is subject to periodic flooding,
to coastal areas invaded by sand,
The concept of ecological villages emerged with the aim of restoring a more favorable ecological balance.
Some villages in the Aitui district,
where Mr. lives
Nguyen Thanh Hen with his family,
are genuine successes.
We replanted and recreated a microclimate that favours the creation of orchards and ponds suitable for developing aquaculture ponds.
By setting up a small fish farm near his home,
Mr.
Nguyen Thanh Hen has acquired a significant additional resource that fits directly into the coastal rehabilitation program.
In this village,
where there is a particular awareness of environmental issues,
We do not hesitate to experiment with the advantages that biomass offers in addition to traditional wood-fire heating.
Thanks to the presence of a pig farm near the kitchen,
In a way, Madame Guyenne Tannhain enjoys an almost modern level of comfort.
Gas is made from pig excrement.
Yes,
That's how this tank fills with gas.
This allows us to cook directly on the stove.
It's very practical.
NOW,
with gas,
It's very comfortable.
Formerly,
They only cooked with wood.
And it was very unpleasant.
Whereas now,
No more wood-chopping chores.
Especially since I was the one who went.
Paradoxically,
in this district of Haiti,
despite global warming,
The temperature is dropping.
Proof that anything is possible.
always take action.
Formerly,
in our country,
There were only large sand dunes.
It was very, very hot.
And today,
even if we have storms and wind,
with the trees,
The weather is still much better.
We can get into the shade now.
Thanks to the foliage.
Today,
Nature is no longer what it used to be.
If you want to live with us for a few more years,
You need to eat.
It was so hot back then.
Tell,
How did you manage to walk on the sand back then?
You could barely set foot on the sand.
Do you realize?
Barely had I set foot on the sand.
It was so hot.
But I still needed to be able to walk on that sand.
SO,
I was forced to wear sandals.
Yes,
wear sandals.
I was the only one.
All the neighbors made fun of me.
With the consequences of deforestation,
The environment has been profoundly altered.
Faced with these upheavals,
The Vietnamese government has taken several initiatives with a number of organizations.
to encourage people to protect the forest.
Moreover,
Reforestation programs have been launched so that rural inhabitants have a chance to one day rediscover the traditional Vietnamese forest.
Reforestation guidelines are not new.
Uncle Ho, already
Ho Chi Minh City
the victor of Dien Bien Phu and the war against the Americans,
after the fall of Saigon in 1975,
had launched a vast reforestation campaign to mitigate the disastrous effects of intensive bombing.
But if the government has created jobs for forest rangers,
He was unable to prevent commercial exploitation of the forests.
Today,
A vast program is being implemented to limit intensive exploitation and organize the timber trade.
Mr. Nguyen Hinh Tan,
him,
modestly followed Uncle Ho's advice by planting his small forest.
If we encourage reforestation,
It's because when a tree is planted,
Its roots plunge into the earth and thereby aerate the soil.
The flowing water can then penetrate the ground and replenish the underground aquifers.
The leaves that fall from the trees,
As for them,
cover the ground and create a kind of plant carpet that retains moisture.
In the shade of the foliage,
It allows temperatures to be lowered significantly.
And those trees,
When were they planted?
Oh dear?
All this forest?
I planted this 5-6 years ago.
And throughout that entire area,
Are there any particular animal species?
No.
No,
Not much anymore.
You know.
Today,
There are only wild geese left.
When I arrived here...
I cleared everything and planted large trees.
But now,
There aren't many animals left.
And that's a real shame.
But in the past,
There were indeed tigers here.
Yes,
Of course,
Of course.
There were lots of animals.
Not only were there tigers,
But there were also bears,
wild boars.
But all of that,
That was a long time ago,
for a very long time.
The only way for the animals to return,
It's about making people understand that we absolutely must protect the forest and all the natural resources it represents.
On one hand,
People's mentality has not yet evolved sufficiently.
because they continue to cut down trees and hunt animals.
for the sole purpose of serving their own personal interests.
On the other hand,
Animals live thanks to the forest.
But men exploit their territory.
and now,
Every time animals sense the presence of humans,
They disappear.
In Vietnam,
The example is often set by elders who have demonstrated the strength of their conviction through their commitment.
Like Mr.
Lee,
now retired,
who regularly receives many visits from his admirers,
because he is a true national hero.
Mr. Lee is known throughout the country.
He was nicknamed the man who will save the forest.
Sir
Lee succeeded where even the most eminent scientists have failed.
He is the only one to have successfully grown seeds from a precious wood.
particularly sought after,
the oil.
But his success doesn't stop there.
While Vietnam is currently the world's leading producer of pepper,
It's surely partly thanks to him.
He not only discovered the miracle of the wood of huine,
but also realized that the pepper plant was growing incredibly well by twining around its trunk.
In 15 years,
He made a real fortune and is now cited as an example.
He revealed his secrets because many people...
in the region,
they in turn began to cultivate oilseeds and pepper plants.
"You need to have been in business for a long time and have a lot of experience.
When I see all the diplomas and awards you have received,
It's very impressive.
"Ah,
"You're talking about everything that's hanging there!"
"What degree do you have?"
"I have a diploma received from the Prime Minister,"
that was at
Hanoi.
And then I also received the environmental award.
And also several awards from the Poambin region.
And all those diplomas,
all these prizes,
Where did you put them?
I put them in my son's house.
my eldest son.
So your son is the one who keeps everything?
Yes, indeed.
in his room,
That way we'll be able to create a proper memorial at his home.
Today,
Mr.'s sons
Lee took over.
They exploit the forests planted by their father and sell seedlings.
Scientists have been trying for years,
and by all means,
to grow oil tree seeds in the laboratory.
But they never succeeded.
Mr.
Lee,
him,
He had the patience to trust nature and his intuition.
It was a day,
You were still very young when our father came here.
There was absolutely nothing there on that hill.
But that's where he started planting.
And look at what it looks like today.
Actually,
He started with seeds he brought back from the forest.
He brought them home and had the idea of ​​soaking them for a while.
before planting them in the garden.
That's how he managed to make them multiply.
And that's how he created the first forest.
And then he sold the plants to lots of people all over the country.
It's our heritage.
We really need to take care of it.
Beyond the human impact,
Link,
thanks to his expertise,
It also analyzes the industrial effects that modify the environment.
There are more and more industrial activities,
of cars,
means of transport that pollute and have direct effects on the general climate.
It's high time there was better collaboration between those who make the laws.
governments and populations.
This is the only solution to improve the situation.
The concession for this silver mine was granted to a company for a period of 50 years.
But the operators had to reach an agreement with the residents of the municipality.
SO,
after having exploited all this land,
Do you have a plan to rehabilitate the place?
Of course.
When we stop mining the silver mine,
We have committed to...
to restore everything and replant trees.
This is the result of an agreement reached with the people of the region.
We've already replanted some there.
Ultimately,
over there,
along the construction site,
Oh yes,
I see,
It's good.
Yes,
It's been two or three years already.
Environmental destruction,
logging,
industrial expansion,
natural disaster.
If all of this is not countered by a proactive environmental approach,
Vietnam faces great risks for its future.
Faced with global warming, which amplifies the effects of the monsoon every year,
We must therefore react.
While the resources needed to combat the unleashing of the elements are considerable,
Prevention efforts among at-risk populations remain,
She,
easier to implement.
To make a lasting impression on the younger generation,
Local officials do not hesitate to communicate with striking images.
You see there,
Look,
Look at the children.
In 2007,
The water level has reached this far.
But you know,
Perhaps one day the water will rise above this mark.
It can very well rise above that.
Because of the changing climate,
We need to know that we will have floods every year now.
We need to be proactive and responsible in order to fight against these disasters.
It's important to understand this,
the water level sometimes reaches this height,
but it can really go higher.
It can exceed that.
You need to be prepared in order to protect yourself and your property.
And we must fight against the floods because, I repeat,
every year,
every year at our house,
There will be floods.
I saw so many children drown in the floods,
So many children die in disasters,
that I hope the future...
Future generations will no longer have to live through this terrible tragedy.
For my part,
as a mother,
I hope,
I wish...
I truly wish for my children to have a better life.
I would like the future to hold fewer difficulties for them.
And what I desire more than anything,
It's so they no longer have to suffer the wrath of the monsoon.
If there is one word that unites an entire nation,
that is indeed aquam which means
...optimism in Vietnamese.
An optimism whose finest example lies in the relationship of an entire people with water.
Water will always be an ally, not an enemy.
As proof,
the numerous festivals that reveal the veneration that all Vietnamese people have for him,
despite the suffering they inflict upon them.
If we celebrate water with such fervor as a true deity,
that is because she provides the three essential hands,
rice,
Fish and fruit.
Facing off in a fratricidal competition then testifies to the energy that an entire people is capable of mustering to exorcise the threats of water and enjoy its benefits.